You did say something that caught my
eye, and that is that your training,
your CIA training
was critical for your survival in a
tough prison. Saved my life. Explain it.
At sentencing, my attorneys asked the
judge to recommend that I go to a
minimum security work camp. The
prosecution had no objection. So, she
says, "Okay, minimum security work
camp." The CIA was furious.
So, they asked DOJ to send me instead to
a higher security prison.
When I got to the prison,
I said, "No, no, I'm supposed to be
across the street at the camp." And the
guard said, "Not according to my
paperwork, you're not." I told myself,
"Take it easy. There's nothing you can
do. Don't say anything. You'll end up in
solitary." It took me 4 days to get
access to a phone, and I called the the
lawyers. I said, "Listen, they put me in
the actual prison with the mafia dons
and the pedophiles and the the drug
cartels and lots of murderers."
But I I also had to work with the CIA
for 15 years. Yeah. Um
Yeah, I did.
>> So, how did that help you? That's an
interesting story. I ended up writing a
book about it called Doing Time Like a
Spy: How the CIA Taught Me to Survive
and Thrive in Prison. I took these life
lessons that the CIA taught me. Some of
them were kind of tongue-in-cheek, like
like admit nothing, deny everything,
make counter-accusations. But others
were serious, like
let others do your dirty work,
for example.
Um
form strategic alliances.
>> the child rapist and the murderer to do,
you know, kitchen duty for you or do
janitorial duty in the prison?
>> Do we have time for a short example?
>> Yeah, of course. There was a serial
killer in my in my housing unit. We
called Truck. He was a long-distance
truck driver, and he would pick up
prostitutes at truck stops and and
murder them and throw them out of the
truck.
This is Great place to live. Oh, it's
great having these people just, you
know, around you 24 hours a day. This
was before DNA testing. So, he ended up
strangling a woman who survived and she
identified him. She got the license
plate of the truck as he was driving
away. So, he was doing 40 years.
And
for reasons that were never clear to me,
he constantly sought my approval.
He would say things like, "Oh, John, I
saved you a seat in the TV room for the
Steelers game this Sunday." I'd say,
"Thanks, Truck."
Um
there was another man though who wanted
to move into my
my cell.
But we had a rule in our cell, no
pedophiles and no rats. So, I said, "You
a pedophile?" He said, "No." I said,
"What's your crime?" He said, "Murder
for hire." I said, "I don't think I like
that any better than pedophilia."
I said, "What were the circumstances?"
He said, "Oh, I I have a gambling
problem. I owed the mob 100 grand. I
took out a life insurance policy on my
business partner and I hired a hitman to
kill him."
And I said, "And you ratted out the the
shooter." He said, "Well, they offered
me 20 years." I said, "No rats, no
pedophiles." Well, he didn't like that.
One day, I'm sitting in the
in the TV room with Truck watching the
Steelers game
and uh
it just so happened that day that Jake
Tapper had come up to the prison to
interview me.
And so, I was called down to the
lieutenant's office to sign a waiver.
>> If you want to take shots of fake Jake,
all right ahead. Feel free. Just take a
fire away.
I don't like Jake Tapper. Go ahead.
So, I got called down to the
lieutenant's office to sign the waiver.
Normally, if you're called to the
lieutenant's office, it's because you
did something and you're going to
solitary.
So, I'm sitting there watching the
Steelers game and this rat didn't see
that I'm sitting a foot and a half away
from him and he says to the guy next to
him, "Did you hear Kyriacou got called
to the lieutenant's office?" He said,
"That guy's a rat. He went down there to
rat us out." Well, if you call somebody
a rat,
blood's going to be spilled.
>> Yep. I didn't react in any way. And
Truck said, "That guy just called you a
rat."
But I saw my opportunity, and I said,
"Half an hour ago I heard him call you a
pedophile."
And without saying a word,
Truck got up and beat him almost to
death.
They had to land a helicopter in the
yard to life-flight him to Pittsburgh.
>> It's a CIA op. So, you make your
accusation.
>> it was. I ran an op. And so, Truck got
an extra 5 years and got sent to the
maximum security penitentiary. Got rid
of him. And then, the murder-for-hire
guy, after 6 weeks in the hospital, came
back. Somebody had told him what I did,
and he came back with his head down
saying, "I'm sorry I called you a rat.
I'll never do it again." And I said,
"Listen, cuz I'm only going to say this
once.
If I ever hear my name cross your lips
ever again,
you're dead."
And he said, "I understand."
>> You're You're not that intimidating.
>> No, I'm a nice guy. No, no, no. No, and
I'm not saying that negatively. No, I'm
I'm agreeing with you.
>> You don't look like the guy that's
jacked up in the,
you know, in the weight room at the
prison outside, you know, lifting Yeah,
yeah, yeah. Rule number four, let others
do your dirty work. Wow.
Uh that's an interesting that That's
That's pretty fascinating. Here's the
thing.
So, in prison, you're right. If you're a
rat, if you're a snitch,
>> Mhm. if you're a pedophile, you are
prisoners there's code, they have their
own standards. Mhm. You don't want to be
associated with them. That's right. But
you're a CIA guy.
>> Mhm. They know why you're in there.
>> Mhm.
Okay? How did they react?
>> that was going to be a terrible problem.
>> I thought I'm on paper I would think it
would be, too. Well, there happened to
be an Italian Yeah. in prison. And when
I I use air quotes, I I mean because
their names Gambino, Lucchese, Bonanno,
uh Genovese, they became my dearest,
closest friends. Why? Why Why did
>> Because there was one guy who read in
the New York Times, shout out to Mark
Lanza,
one of my dearest friends,
he read in the New York Times 4 days
before my arrival that I was going to
that prison. Mhm. And
just
because
he went to every single Italian in the
prison and he said, "Listen, there's a
CIA guy coming here.
He's not an FBI agent." He said, "FBI
are cops and rats. CIA protected us from
the Muslims.
And so we should welcome him."
And when I arrived, scared to death,
Open arms.
>> Open arms. I never had a moment's
trouble. Not one. No not one fight. I
gained
>> attack. Never. When word got around I
was with the Italians and I was sitting
with them in the cafeteria, it was hands
off. I gained 35 lb in prison because
the Italians had a crooked guard on the
payroll who would bring in the pork loin
and the wine for the Marsala sauce and
the fresh vegetables. Right. And we ate
like kings.
My wife said to me one day, "What's
happening to you?"
>> This is straight out of Goodfellas, you
know that?
>> out of Goodfellas. Yeah. It was real
life. They treated me like a king. Very
entertaining. All right, let me let me
move on cuz I've got a lot of ground to
cover with you.
We might disagree on this. Um I think we
probably will.
And if you go back and it's the issue of
enhanced interrogation.
>> Mhm. And there were three people that
were waterboarded.
>> Mhm. Okay? And 39 people that got
enhanced interrogation.
You've spoken out against it and I want
to hear why.
There are 10 specific things that they
do
when it comes to enhanced interrogation.
They'll slap you in the face, they'll
get in your face, they'll grab you by
and you know, get in your grill.
Okay, the worst one that I read
>> So, you're not against that?
No. No. You know, a lot of people I
think missed
>> do people characterize you that way
then? Cuz
>> cuz they missed the nuance or they
decided that it was it was
expedient for them to ignore the nuance.
Okay.
I agree with you. A smack in the belly
makes a cracking sound, leaves a hand
print, it's a little embarrassing, not
torture. Right. Right.
>> That's called pain day in my martial
arts training.
And I I get that. My sensei strong and
it's like I have to stand up. First I
get this like it's for calcification,
you know, and it's hard and I'm going to
bring him on the pod one day and then I
have to stand there and I go like this
and he's like take boom, boom, like
really hits you.
And he can throw This guy's been doing
it for 45 years. He'll drop me on the
fifth shot almost every time, but he
wants me to take as much as I can take.
Um so, that's why you know, everyone's
become a big baby like
Do you like hockey? Right over your
shoulder it says Hannity, that's you
know, I love my Florida Panthers. Behind
me
right there. Florida Panthers.
>> go. I got over there Matthew Tkachuk's
um Oh. uh gold medal
>> Oh. uh winning jersey that he signed to
me which is cool. We're going to move it
over here.
And so, I love hockey and I have my
Panthers belt up there.
>> I love it. Pretty cool, right? So, why
do I read
But it's like people all fighting in
sports is horrible. I'm like, okay, grow
up. My dad used to always say
he would go to a
a fight and a hockey game broke out.
Exactly.
Did you doubt like hockey?
>> Oh, he did. Pittsburgh Penguins for
decades.
>> Penguins had some good years.
>> Yeah, we did. Uh Mario Lemieux The best.
>> was he was phenomenal. I used to love
the Broad Street Bullies growing up. Oh
my god.
>> but I digress. So, you're not So, why do
I read everywhere that you're against
enhanced interrogation? You're not,
you're telling me.
I was against very specific
techniques that I believed were torture,
and I'll tell you why.